<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://n-reeves.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://n-reeves.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-24T22:19:20+00:00</updated><id>https://n-reeves.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Professional homepage for Nick Reeves. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Neural Speech Enhancement - Explained</title><link href="https://n-reeves.github.io/blog/2025/speech-enhancement-network/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neural Speech Enhancement - Explained"/><published>2025-01-24T01:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-24T01:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://n-reeves.github.io/blog/2025/speech-enhancement-network</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://n-reeves.github.io/blog/2025/speech-enhancement-network/"><![CDATA[<hr/> <h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Speech enhancement aims to improve the audibility and clarity of speech in noisy or reverberant environments. This project explores a neural network-based approach for reducing background noise and echo while enhancing speech quality. The system leverages a Complex U-Net architecture trained to process noisy and reverberant audio, focusing on single-channel, two-speaker scenarios.</p> <p><em>Disclaimer on generative AI use:</em> This document was created with the help of ChatGPT, which summarized key content from a more comprehensive paper I wrote. I have verified the accuracy of the information listed here and edited the content where appropriate.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="background">Background</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Audio Signal</strong>: A time-domain representation of sound that can be transformed into frequency components using techniques like the Short-Time Fourier Transform (STFT).</li> <li><strong>STFT</strong>: A method that splits an audio signal into overlapping frames, applying the Fourier transform to each to yield time-frequency representations.</li> <li><strong>STFT Coefficients</strong>: Complex numbers representing the amplitude (magnitude) and phase of audio signals at specific time-frequency bins.</li> <li><strong>Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs)</strong>: Neural networks designed to extract features from grid-like data, such as images or spectrograms.</li> <li><strong>Spectrograms</strong>: Visual representations of the frequency content of a signal over time, derived from STFT magnitudes.</li> <li><strong>U-Net</strong>: An encoder-decoder network architecture with skip connections, commonly used for image segmentation and extended here for speech enhancement.</li> <li><strong>Complex Convolutions</strong>: Extensions of convolution operations to the complex domain, enabling models to process both magnitude and phase components.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="experiment-design">Experiment Design</h2> <h3 id="objective">Objective</h3> <p>To enhance speech clarity by reducing background noise and reverberation in two-speaker audio mixtures.</p> <h3 id="dataset">Dataset</h3> <ol> <li><strong>LibriMix Dataset</strong>: <ul> <li>8,000 samples of fully overlapping, 8 kHz two-speaker mixtures.</li> <li>Divided into 75% training, 12.5% validation, and 12.5% testing subsets, ensuring no speaker overlap between train and test sets.</li> <li>Additive noise was applied for augmentation.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>MIT Impulse Response Dataset</strong>: <ul> <li>271 impulse responses simulating real-world reverberant environments.</li> <li>Partitioned into 70% training, 15% validation, and 15% testing splits.</li> </ul> </li> </ol> <h3 id="data-augmentation">Data Augmentation</h3> <ul> <li>Random cropping was applied to training data to introduce noise variations.</li> <li>Reverberation was added to mixtures using impulse responses from the MIT dataset.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h3 id="loss-function">Loss Function</h3> <p>The loss function minimizes the difference between the predicted and target STFT coefficients:</p> \[\mathcal{L} = \sum_{t,f} \left( | \hat{R}_{t,f} - R_{t,f} |^2 + | \hat{I}_{t,f} - I_{t,f} |^2 \right)\] <p>Where \(\hat{R}_{t,f}\) and \(\hat{I}_{t,f}\) are the predicted real and imaginary components, and \(R_{t,f}\) and \(I_{t,f}\) are the target components at time \(t\) and frequency \(f\).</p> <hr/> <h3 id="evaluation-metrics">Evaluation Metrics</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Signal-to-Distortion Ratio (SDR)</strong>: Measures the quality of the enhanced signal relative to the ground truth.</li> </ul> \[\text{SDR} = 10 \log_{10} \frac{\|s_{\text{target}}\|^2}{\|s_{\text{error}}\|^2}\] <p>Where \(s_{\text{target}}\) is the ground truth signal, and \(s_{\text{error}}\) is the difference between the ground truth and the predicted signal.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Perceptual Evaluation of Speech Quality (PESQ)</strong>: Quantifies speech quality as perceived by humans.</li> </ul> \[\text{PESQ} = f_{\text{pesq}}(s_{\text{enhanced}}, s_{\text{reference}})\] <p>Where \(f_{\text{pesq}}\) is the PESQ evaluation function, \(s_{\text{enhanced}}\) is the enhanced signal, and \(s_{\text{reference}}\) is the reference signal.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Short-Time Objective Intelligibility (STOI)</strong>: Estimates the intelligibility of enhanced speech.</li> </ul> \[\text{STOI} = f_{\text{stoi}}(s_{\text{enhanced}}, s_{\text{reference}})\] <p>Where \(f_{\text{stoi}}\) is the STOI evaluation function, \(s_{\text{enhanced}}\) is the enhanced signal, and \(s_{\text{reference}}\) is the reference signal.</p> <h2 id="architecture">Architecture</h2> <p>In audio processing, neural architectures are often designed to work with spectrograms, as this simplifies the handling of complex numbers. It also enables the use of existing image processing techniques, such as convolutional neural networks (CNNs), without issues. However, this approach requires discarding phase information, which can lead to challenges depending on the task.</p> <ul> <li>The network cannot leverage phase information during training.</li> <li>If the system is designed to work with spectrograms (e.g., through masking), the output will be real-valued.</li> </ul> <p>In the context of speech enhancement, I aimed to create a mask that could be applied directly to the output. By applying a mask rather than synthesizing an enhanced signal, the stability of the network is improved. Additionally, when a network is trained to generate a magnitude spectrogram, phase information must be approximated using techniques like Griffin-Lim, or a different system must be employed to convert the real-valued coefficients back to the signal domain.</p> <h3 id="complex-convolutional-layers">Complex Convolutional Layers</h3> <p>A complex convolutional filter \(W = A + iB\) applied to a complex input \(h = x + yi\) produces:</p> \[Wh = (A * x - B * y) + i(B * x + A * y)\] <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/speech-enhance/complexconv-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/speech-enhance/complexconv-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/speech-enhance/complexconv-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/speech-enhance/complexconv.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Real vs. Complex Convolution" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <label for="output-audio-example">Diagram from Choi, H.-S. et al. (2019) (author redacted paper) </label> </div> </div> <p>This idea was proposed by Trabelsi, C. et al. (2018), who also extend the logic to activation functions and different normalization techniques.</p> <h3 id="complex-u-net">Complex U-Net</h3> <p>The architecture consists of an encoder-decoder network with complex convolutions:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Encoder</strong>: Sequential layers of complex convolutions and downsampling that capture compact representations of the input spectrogram.</li> <li><strong>Decoder</strong>: Transpose convolutions that reconstruct the spectrogram from encoded features.</li> <li><strong>Skip Connections</strong>: Feature maps from encoder layers are concatenated with corresponding decoder layers to preserve spatial information.</li> </ol> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/speech-enhance/complexskipnet-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/speech-enhance/complexskipnet-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/speech-enhance/complexskipnet-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/speech-enhance/complexskipnet.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Real Valued Skip U-Net from Kothapally, V. et al. 2020" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <label for="output-audio-example">Diagram from Kothapally, V. et al. (2020)</label> </div> </div> <p>My design extends the real-valued U-Net for speech dereverberation design proposed by Kothapally, V. et al. (2020) to the complex domain. It should be noted that my original inspiration for this combination of ideas was from Choi, H.-S. et al. (2019), although the author redacted the paper due to flaws in their methodology.</p> <h3 id="real-valued-skip-u-net-vs-complex-u-net">Real-Valued Skip U-Net vs. Complex U-Net</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Real-Valued U-Net</strong>: Operates only on magnitude spectrograms, combining the output with the noisy phase.</li> <li><strong>Complex U-Net</strong>: Processes the full complex STFT coefficients, preserving phase information.</li> </ul> <p><img src="assets/real_valued_skip_unet.png" alt="Real-Valued Skip U-Net Architecture"/> <img src="assets/complex_conv_layer.png" alt="Complex Convolutional Layer"/></p> <hr/> <h2 id="post-processing-with-signal-processing">Post-Processing with Signal Processing</h2> <p>The U-Net applies a tanh activation function to the complex masking coefficients, which stabilizes the output but imposes a strict bound on the signal’s intensity. This often results in a reduced perceived loudness. To address this, I designed a custom loudness normalization algorithm that adjusts the output’s amplitude envelope, ensuring it closely matches the input’s amplitude envelope without any coefficients exceeding the input’s intensity.</p> <p>The key steps are:</p> <ol> <li><strong>STFT Magnitude Adjustment</strong>: <ul> <li>Compute scaling factors for each time-frequency coefficent based on the ratio of the magnitude spectrogram of the input signal to the magnitude spectrogram of the output signal.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Normalization Formula</strong>: <ul> <li>If the network reduced the magnitude of a coeffient in the output relative to the min and max of the input and output spectrograms, we do not boost the magnitude of those coefficents</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Reconstruction</strong>: <ul> <li>Apply the inverse STFT (ISTFT) to the normalized audio to generate the final time-domain signal.</li> </ul> </li> </ol> <p>More formally, let \(X\) be the STFT of the input signal, \(Y\) be the STFT of the output signal. Let \(|X|^{\text{norm}}\) and \(|Y|\) be the min-max normalized spectrograms of \(X\) and \(Y\), respectively.</p> <p>The scaling factor \(sf_{ij}\) for each complex coefficient \(Y_{ij}\) is defined as:</p> \[\text{sf}_{ij} = \begin{cases} 1 &amp; \text{if } \frac{|X_{ij}|^{\text{norm}}}{|Y_{ij}|^{\text{norm}}} &lt; 1 \\ \frac{|X_{ij}|}{|Y_{ij}|} &amp; \text{otherwise} \end{cases}\] <p>This scaling factor adjusts the magnitude of \(Y_{ij}\) to match the desired relationship between the input and output signals. Specifically:</p> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>If</strong> $$\frac{</td> <td>X_{ij}</td> <td>^{norm}}{</td> <td>Y_{ij}</td> <td>^{norm}} &lt; 1\(: The magnitude of the coefficient\)Y_{ij}$$ was reduced by the neural network relative to the input signal. In this case, we assume the network tried to reduce the contribution of this coefficient to the strength of signal, so we do not apply the scaling factor. If this ratio is greater than or equal to one, the scaling factor is applied to the complex coefficient.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>Finally, to limit the case where the scaling factor leads to unpleasantly large increases in energy, the scaling factor is limited s.t. the magnitude of each coefficient can’t surpass the magnitude of the input coefficient.</p> <h2 id="recap">Recap</h2> <p>This project implemented a Complex U-Net architecture to enhance speech clarity in noisy and reverberant conditions. The system leverages advanced signal processing for post-processing to normalize loudness and compensate for the U-Net’s bounded outputs. Despite computational and dataset constraints, the model demonstrates effective noise and echo reduction in real-world scenarios.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="assets">Assets</h3> <ul> <li><a href="assets/input_output_spectrogram.png">Input and Output Spectrograms</a></li> <li><a href="assets/audio_example.mp3">Audio Example (Input and Output)</a></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Machine-Learning"/><category term="Audio-Processing"/><category term="speech"/><category term="accessibility"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Noisy environments can make speech more difficult to understand. In this project I explore a novel method for removing background noise and echos for audio files with multiple speakers.]]></summary></entry></feed>